<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King David's case apply'd to King James and King William in a sermon preach'd at Christ-Church, Dublin, on the fifth of November, 1691 / by John Stearne ...</title>
            <author>Stearne, John, 1660-1745.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42759</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875716</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152410</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2296:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King David's case apply'd to King James and King William in a sermon preach'd at Christ-Church, Dublin, on the fifth of November, 1691 / by John Stearne ...</title>
                  <author>Stearne, John, 1660-1745.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Crook ... and are to be sold by Elipha[l?] Dobson ... and by Robert Thornton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and faded with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms IV, 2-4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Irish --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152410:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152410:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>King David's CASE Apply'd To King James AND King William; IN A SERMON Preach'd at <hi>Chriſt-Church, Dublin,</hi> on the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> 1691.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Stearne,</hi> Curate of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> within the Walls; and Chaplain to the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Charles Porter,</hi> Lord High Chancellor, and One of the Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>If your delight be in Thrones and Scepters, O ye Kings of the People, honour Wiſdom, that ye may Reign for evermore.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Wiſdom of Solomon VI. XXI.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Crook</hi> on <hi>Ormonde-Key,</hi> and are to be ſold by Eliſhal <hi>Dolſon</hi> at the <hi>Stationers-Arms</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet,</hi> and by <hi>Robert Thornton,</hi> in <hi>Capel-ſtreet.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:152410:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152410:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON Pſalm IV. Ver. 2, 3, 4.</head>
            <q>
               <p>O Ye Sons of men, how long will ye turn my Glory into Shame? how long will ye love <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anity, and ſeek after leaſing?</p>
               <p>But Know that the Lord hath ſet a part him that is Godly for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: the Lord will hear when I call unto him.</p>
               <p>Stand in aw and ſin not: Commune with your owne heart upon your bed, and be Still.</p>
            </q>
            <p>GOdlineſs ſupports the Throne; and more ſets off a Crown than all its Jewels: it makes a King ſafe in the Protection of Heaven; Strikes his Enemies with Terrour; and in his Subjects raiſes an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of many glorious Dayes under his bleſsed Reign. Such Royal Vertues enrich'd the ſoul of <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. (Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi>) that (as a very faithfull Hiſtorian informes the world) <hi>ab uno ipſo laborantis Imperil modela ſperare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> it might have been reaſonably expected that by him alone the whole Body of the languiſhing Empire ſhou'd have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to an healthful State. And did not the many and great Military, Civil and Religious Accompliſhments (well known unto more than the Chriſtian World, in the fam'd Atchievements) of our preſent Monarch, bear up the linking Hearts of all our Proteſtant Kingdoms, with the juſteſt Hopes of ſeeing (one happy day) all the Miſeries that oppreſs'd or threatned our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152410:3"/>Church and State ſeaſonably remov'd or prevented by his Succeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Arm? And, according to ſuch an Expectation, the careful Providence of God (the All wiſe Diſpoſer of Crowns and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) has been ſo ſignally diſplay'd in a long Series of Mercies to him; in carrying on and in compleating that truly Chriſtian Work; that a man muſt be either willfully blind, in not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, or baſely ungrateful, in not acknowledging that his Royal Perſon was the Chief Inſtrument of God in that ſurprizing Revolution, which is deſervedly the Joy of the preſent Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and which will be the Wonder of future Ages. The ſudden News of ſuch a Deliverer's Coming into <hi>England,</hi> on this memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Day, was I conceive, to many, (as the Angel's Meſſage was unto the Shepherds, at our Saviour's Comlng into the World) Good tydings of great Joy. for, as if he had been a greater Light made to rule the Day of our Deliverance, he ſtill grew ſtronger as he advanc'd; and with his prevailing Beams ſoon diſpel'd thoſe Clouds which had long hung over our Heads, making all black and melancholy round about Us. Yet (as the inconſtant Jews preſently forgat God their Saviour and lightly eſteemed <hi>Moſes</hi> his Servant whom he had choſen to conduct them, with Wonders, towards <hi>Canaan</hi>) how ſoon did too many repine at the forward and almoſt uninterrupted Approaches of their own Happineſs, and Slander the Foot-ſteps of their great Deliverer? Such is the uneaſy humour of ſome that they are always diſcontented under their Oppreſſions, and yet always undervalue the relieving Hand; ſo that neither a Popiſh, nor a Proteſtant King, nor yet a moſt merciful God can pleaſe them. Such diſſatisfi'd Creatures were the Men that both by ſecret and open Methods oppos'd our Royal Pſalmiſt. Tho' God had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>Saul</hi> for his wickedneſs &amp; given his Kingdom to a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that was better than He; and tho' <hi>David</hi> was anointed by <hi>Samuel</hi> at Gods expreſs Command, yet how many in the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> joyn'd their Endeavours with <hi>Saul</hi>'s Malice, to obſtruct <hi>David</hi>'s juſt Acceſſion to the Crown? And, when <hi>Saul</hi> was fall'n ingloriously on the Mountains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> how many labour'd to promote the Intereſt of his Family and to diſturb King <hi>David</hi> in his Poſſeſſion? Not only Forreign Nations (the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> and <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> the <hi>Moabites, Syrians</hi> and <hi>Amalekites</hi>) ſet themſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152410:3"/>againſt him; but (as if there had been a joynt-conſpiracy to croſs the ſix'd Reſolve of Heaven) a conſiderable Number of the Jews comply'd with <hi>Abner</hi>'s deſign, to place <hi>Saul</hi>'s Son upon the Throne. This (as many Judicious Expoſiters do conclude) was the ſpecial Occaſion upon which <hi>David</hi> compos'd the preſent Pſalm. In the firſt Verſe he appeals to God as the Witneſs, Judge and Defender of his righteous Cauſe; gratefully owns his paſt Mercies to him in the Day of Trouble &amp; humbly prays for future; and then in our Text addreſſes his Speech unto the Sons of Men by a double earneſt Interrogation (implying at once the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own Concern and of their Folly in oppoſing him) <hi>How long will ye turn my Glory into Shame? how long will ye love Vanity, and ſeek after lies?</hi> How long will ye think to deprive me of that Honour which God's Goodneſs has conferr'd upon me? How long will ye look upon me as an Ambitious Uſurper and expoſe me as ſuch unto the ſcorn and contempt of the people? How long will ye make it your Buſineſs and Satisfaction to contrive, encourage and carry on ſuch traiterous Counſels, Deſigns and Plots againſt my Life and Crown, as will moſt certainly prove vain Devices and lying Imaginations; moſt groſsly diſappointing all your big Hopes of compaſſing my ruine in the end? God has already often <hi>heard my Prayer, and enlarged me when I was in Diſtreſs;</hi> and therefore <hi>he will hear me when I call upon him</hi> hereafter to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found your Devices. Be not therefore, <hi>O ye Sons of Men!</hi> any longer ſo bold and fooliſh as to perſiſt in ſuch unſucceſsfull and and unjuſt Attempts; but know (aſſuredly) that I am ſo far from ambitiouſlly aſpiring unto the Throne of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that God has qualifi'd me (by his holy Oyl) for the Government of that People, over whom he hath <hi>wonderfully ſet me apart,</hi> or in an extraordinary manner made me King; that I may Act for himſelf, for his Honour in promoting his true Religion in the Land; and thereby advance the Happineſs of all his People com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my Charge.</p>
            <p>Having thus acquainted you with the moſt probable Occaſion of this Pſalm; and given you a very natural Explication of our Text in particular; I ſhall not any further enlarge upon the words as relating to K. <hi>David</hi> and his Enemies, either in <hi>Saul</hi>'s or his own Court; but raiſe from them one Propoſition of more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152410:4"/>general concernment; and fairly apply it to the Double Bleſſing which we ought to celebrate this remarkable Day; Namely, the great deliverance of our three Kingdoms from Popery by the timely Diſcovery of the <hi>Gun-Powder-Treaſon,</hi> to the peaceful K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; and the great Deliverance of the ſame King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, from the ſame miſery, by the ſeaſonable coming of King <hi>William</hi> the Third into <hi>England:</hi> For tho' his Landing was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd on the Fourth of this Month, Providence deferr'd it 'till the Fifth; as if the Birth of ſo great a Prince (of the Antient and moſt Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw</hi>) and his Marriage with ſo great a Princeſs as our now Moſt Gracious Queen, had already ſuficiently ſignaliz'd one Day to after Ages; or as if it wou'd make us more mindful of God's mercies to us on the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering us twice from Popery on the ſame day; in the Years 1605. and 1688. A Year as wonderful for God's bringing ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly King <hi>William</hi>'s Navy to the ſalvation of <hi>England,</hi> as the Year 1588 was for God's deſtroying the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Armada, which (as if it had been really Invincible) proudly threatned <hi>England</hi> with a moſt dreadful Invaſion. So that three days eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this Month of <hi>November</hi> deſerve a more particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark in our Reform'd Kingdoms. The Fourth on which (in the Year 1650) God with an hopeful Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> bleſled, not only the United Provinces (for ſuch a Bleſſing was too great for one particular State) but the whole Proteſtaut world; and on which alſo (in the year 1677) God bleſs'd the ſame Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with a Royal Conſort: The Seventeenth, on which the Light of the Goſpel, after the black Night of Queen Mary's Reign began to ſhine forth in the Glorious Riſing of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth;</hi> And the Fifth, on which a moſt Horrid Work of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was deſign'd for the final Extinction of the ſame Bleſſed Light, but, was (at the very Midnight immediately foregoing) moſt happily diſcover'd, by the wonderful Providence and Mercy of God to her Succeſſor, as well in the defence of the truly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Apoſtolick Faith, as in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt. The Hiſtory of this Damnable Plot, and this unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Diſappointment to the bloody Hopes of <hi>Rome,</hi> will enſily come under this one Propoſition, which (according to my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) I now raiſe from the two firſt Verſes of my Text.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152410:4"/>
            <p>Tho' Godly Kings (wonderfully ſet apart by God) do anſwer Gods expectation in making his true Religion their principal Care, yet the Sons of Men do often vainly endeavour to appoſe their Perſons and to diſturb their Government.</p>
            <p>What can be more evident to all the world than the Truth of this Aſſertion in the many Contrivances &amp; Deſigns againſt K. <hi>James,</hi> both before and after his coming to the Crown of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shou'd I particularly acquaint you with all the illegal, baſe Methods which the Enemies of that Crowned Head took, to hinder his ſucceeding in the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> my diſcourſe wou'd ſoon ſwell beyond the ordinary limits of a Sermon. Therefore (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering eſpecially that moſt of this Honourable Auditory are no ſtrangers to the tranſactions of our own Kingdomes) I ſhall be content to take notice but of one Hiſtorical Paſſage in relation to K. <hi>James,</hi> which may be ſufficient to demonſtrate how vainly the Sons of Men contriv'd &amp; endeavour'd to turn his Glory into Shame.</p>
            <p>This day will tell you that I mean the <hi>Gun-Powder-Treaſon:</hi> A Wickedneſs ſo deteſtable to all that have not caſt of Humanity, and ſo great in it ſelfe, that it neither needs, nor will eaſily allow of any Aggravation. But the more Univerſal and Cruel It was in the Intention of our Enemies, the more gratefully ſhou'd we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the merciful Providence of Almighty God in deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it (as on this day) K. <hi>James,</hi> with the three Eſtates of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> aſſembled in Parliament; to the Glory of his Name and the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion in theſe Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>When many ſecret Plots had been laid in vain and many open Attempts had prov'd unſucceſsful; when neither the thundering Curſes of Four Holy Fathers (<hi>Paul</hi> the IV. <hi>Pius</hi> the V. <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. and <hi>Sixtus</hi> the V.) nor the great Condeſcention of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the IV. cou'd prevail: when neither the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armada nor the <hi>Italian</hi> Arts could ſpeed againſt the Providence of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (which carefully preſerved the Learned and Religious Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to the forty fifth Year of her Reign, and the ſixty ninth of her Age) Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the VIII (wiſely foreſeeing the vanity of ſtriving againſt a Monarch that was ſo much the delight and care of Heaven) thought it the moſt politick way, to provide timely againſt any other Heretick's ſucceeding in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152410:5"/>Throne of <hi>England.</hi> And the more effectually to compaſs this Deſign of His Holineſs, two <hi>Breves</hi> were ſpeedily diſpatch'd into <hi>England;</hi> ſtrictly enjoyning both the Clergy and Laity not to ſuffer any but a ſworn Papiſt to take Poſſeſſion of the Crown, after Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s death; or (which was the ſame) not to let K. <hi>James</hi> be King of <hi>England.</hi> From this Command of the Pope, the <hi>Gun-Powder-Treaſon</hi> (or the Plot of blowing up the Parliament houſe) (according to <hi>Camden</hi> and other good Hiſtorians) took its Riſe; for theſe Breves had ſo powerfully wrought upon <hi>Catesby</hi> (the Contriver) that (altho' his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Deſign had been long negotiated in vain) he could never be quiet; nor content to be damn'd alone: but having by the ready Aſſiſtance of the Devil, luckily hit upon this compendious method of deſtruction by <hi>Gun-Powder;</hi> and thinking the Plot of ſome of his party againſt the King's particular life, but a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull under taking, and not any conſiderable ſervice to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Cauſe; he brought ſeveral, (by degrees) into his own Conſpiracy. A deſign which (as we learn from the Conſeſſion of <hi>Guido Faux</hi> (the perſon that boldly undertook to lay the lighted Match unto the Trains of <hi>Gun-Powder</hi>) <hi>Catesby</hi> judg'd moſt, proper, becauſe it was ſitteſt that Juſtice and Puniſhment ſhou'd be executed in that Place where their Religion had been (in their opinion) unjuſtly ſuppreſs'd by Penal Laws. But were the Jeſuits unconcern'd in a Plot for Murdering an Heretical King and People? No certainly: it had fix'd an eternal Blot upon their Character, had they been idle when their great Maſter the Devil (who was a Murderer from the Beginning) was cloſe at Work: Theſe ſiery Spirits therefore (beſides other Encouragement and Aſſiſtance) aſſur'd the Laity of a plenary Abſolution; ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd the Scruple of their tender Conſciences about deſtroying the Righteous with the Wicked (Catholicks and Hereticks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) and more ſtrictly oblig'd them All to perform their Oath of Secrecy and Perſeverance in the great Undertaking, by their own addred Sacrament. All this being done; and all the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Materials (not for building but) for blowing up the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe (being at length convey'd into a convenient, hired Cellar, the joyful Day drew near: but the Letter ſent unto a Noble Lord, from one of the Conſpirators (to diſwade him from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152410:5"/>appearing in the Parliament houſe, on the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> and upon a deliberate, repeated Review of which the <hi>Gun-Powder</hi> Plot was happily diſcover'd) was miſtaken in telling him, that God and Man concur'd at this time to puniſh the Iniquity of the Times. The <hi>Sons of Men</hi> indeed, were ready; but God (with a watchful Eye of Mercy and Compaſſion) ſaw the nearneſs of our danger, and all the Plotting of our Enemies? Tis God's time and Prerogative to ſave in the greateſt extremity of Danger: to ſave <hi>Iſaac</hi> from the very Altar, <hi>Daniel</hi> from the Den of Lions; and the three Children from the burning fiery Furnace. Such a Deliverance looks like the Deliverance of a God; &amp; ſuch a ſeaſonable Salvation does moſt magnifie his Power, his Wiſdom and his Mercy. So far was the Mercileſs Project for an utter Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of the Proteſtant Religion, carry'd on with all imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Secrecy, that for all the fruſtrated Attempts in Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Reign towards a Reſetlement of <hi>Rome's</hi> Supremacy in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Her overjoy'd Agents promis'd themſelves now an ample Recompenſe and Satisfaction, in their effecting this Maſter-Piece of Villany, that might Superſede the Labour of any other Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Contrivances. But, tho, <hi>Rome</hi> had brought the Mighty Work unto the Birth, She wanted Strength to bring forth. How vain is the Devil's and the Jeſuit's Conſult! how unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully do they Club for the Ruin of a Kingdom when Heaven is pleas'd to Thwart their Deſtructive Deſigns! They may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently ſay (as in the forementioned Letter to the Lord <hi>Mount-eagle</hi>) Men ſhall receive a <hi>Terrible Blow,</hi> and yet ſhall not ſee who hurt them; They may pray for the Succeſs of any Bloody Deſign againſt all they Damn for Hereticks (as the <hi>Gun-Powder Traytors</hi> did) <hi>Proſper, O Lord, their Pains that labour in this Cauſe, day and night; Let Hereſie vaniſh like Smoke, and let the Memory of it periſh with a Crack;</hi> all this while that God unto whom nothing is ſecret, to whom the <hi>darkneſs and light are both alike,</hi> beholds all their Revengfull Labours; ſees ev'ry Step they ſilently advance in their Deſigns; and laughs at their Folly. He hears their Uncharitable Prayers; but it is to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them, for the Salvation of his Anointed, and the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his People. Many Devices are in their Hearts; but <hi>the Counſel of the Lord, and that alone ſhall ſtand; even when the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152410:6"/>fall by their own Coxtrivances;</hi> as the <hi>Gun-Powder Traytors</hi> did: Some of them (among whom was <hi>Catesby,</hi> the Subtile In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venter of the Plot) being Diſabled by the Providential Blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of <hi>Gun-Powder</hi> it ſelf, which they were preparing for the Deſtruction of others; as if this had been purpoſely deſign'd to make them more ſenſible of their lately intended Miſchief: Some being actually kill'd in their haſty Flight, upon the Unexpected Diſcovery of their Bloody Purpoſe; particularly, by One Shot, both <hi>Catesby</hi> and <hi>Percy;</hi> from whoſe Dwelling the Powder was brought undiſcover'd, into the Cellar under the Parliament, Houſe: And others, being apprehended, experienc'd how Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſicial the Plot won'd be (as their Confeſſors told them) in the Conſequences of it; as Beneficial as being fairly Hang'd for Treaſon. Thus was <hi>The Lord known by the Judgment which he Executed; By trapping thus the Wicked in the works of their own Hands.</hi> And ſince God did ſo opportunely deliver our Fore-Fathers, at the very Mid-night before that Morning in which they were appointed for the Slaughter, by ſo Great, Surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and Wonderful a Mercy all the Sons of After Generations ſhou'd be Confirm'd in a Comfortable Hope of God's Favour towards them, when their Enemies ſeem to be in the greateſt probability of compaſſing their Deſtruction: For <hi>God is the ſame ysſterday, to day and for ever: his Hand is not ſhorten'd that he cannot ſave</hi> Now, as well as in Former Ages, Godly Kings and States profeſſing his Holy and Eternal Truth. In Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Diſtreſs therefore, let the Reſolution of every one of us be (like that of <hi>Eliphaz</hi> in the book of <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>I will ſeck unto God and unto God will I commit my Cauſe: unto God who doth great things and unſearchable; marvelous things without number: who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointeth the Devices of the Crafty, ſo that their hands cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Emerpriſe: he taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs; and the counſel of the froward is carry'd headlong: but he ſaveth the poor from the Sword and from the hand of the Mighty.</hi> God does often give ſuch a Deliverance to his People as is joyn'd with the Conſuſion of their Enemies: The ſame Sea open'd a Way for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and a Grave for the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> So that the Plots of the Wicked are vain; not only becauſe they are commonly fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in their Hopes of ruining, by them, Religious Kings and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152410:6"/>States; but alſo, becauſe they prove in the end moſt deſtrnctive, of their own Temporal as well as Eternal Happineſs. Thus tho' the <hi>Gun-Powder Traytors</hi> ſaid (in effect) among themſelves, <hi>Come and let us root them out that they may be no more a People;</hi> that the very Name of Proteſtant <hi>may be no more in Remembrance;</hi> yet <hi>they imagined ſuch a Miſchievous Device as they were not able to perform: they digged a Pit and ſunk into the midſt of it themſelves:</hi> Their Intended Miſchief againſt the Lord's Anointed, like Arrows ſhot againſt Heaven, <hi>return'd upon their own Heads, and their Wickedneſs fell upon their own Pates.</hi> So periſhed thoſe Diſcontented Gentlemen; <hi>and ſo let all their Enemies periſh, O Lord; but let them that love thee be joyful and glad in thee; and let all ſuch as delight in thy Salvation ſay alway, the Lord be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this Duty of Thankſgiving may be more cheerfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, let Us now (our Propoſition rais'd from the two firſt Verſes of our Text being diſpatch'd) take into Our Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Third Verſe (containing the Royal Pſalmiſt's Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, inferr'd from his foregoing Addreſs to God and Man) and Apply it to the Caſe of all ſuch as are diſaffected to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government <hi>Stand in awe and ſin not: Commune with your own Heart upon your Bed and be ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When we are withdrawn from the Diſtracting Noiſe and Hurry of the world; and the Stillneſs of Night favour's our Recollected Thoughts, we are well diſpos'd for a Solemn Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation on the moſt weighty Matters; for a ſerions Reflection on our own ways; on our Duty to God and the King. At ſuch a Seaſon therefore do's the Pſalmiſt adviſe his Enemies (who had long in vain oppos'd his Government) to reaſon with themſelves about the wickedneſs of their Undutiful Carriage towards him; and to have an awful Regard to the Omnipreſent, Omniſcient and Almighty God, as a ſpecial means to keep them from ſinning againſt his Anointed; for Plots carry'd on againſt Godly Kings, God interprets as Acted againſt his Divine Majeſty, whoſe Vicegerents they are in this lower World. Such is King <hi>David</hi>'s Confidence in the Juſtice of his Cauſe, that he ſeems wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to referr the whole matter unto their own Conſciences: wou'd they but lay aſide all Paſſion, Pride, Revenge' or Private
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152410:7"/>Intereſt; and give themſelves time to judge calmly of things according to Reaſon &amp; Equity; he does not in the leaſt doubt, but that upon ſuch a deliberate <hi>Communing</hi> with themſelves about the Folly of their Proceedings, they wou'd ſoon <hi>be ſtill</hi> or deſiſt from all Traiterous Deſigns and Seditious Practices.</p>
            <p>Here then, let us a little while reaſon together, about a quiet Submiſſion to that Mighty Monarch whoſe <hi>Glory</hi> too many have vainly endeavour'd <hi>to turn into Shame;</hi> tho' God has wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſet him apart for the Preſervation of his People and the True Religion, in more than our own Kingdoms,</p>
            <p>For the Reſtoration and Security of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Worſhip, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Plots againſt King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> were Contriv'd and Carry'd on. but Heaven diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed all. And as the like Reaſon (or Pretence rather) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd <hi>the Sons of Men</hi> in the Laſt Reign, to make uſe of the moſt Unjuſt Methods and moſt Lamentable Shifts to put King <hi>William</hi> for everby the Succeſſion; ſo the ſame God did not only enable him to Conquer all thoſe Difficulties, but has alſo ſince, Confirm'd him in the Poſſeſſion of the Throne by a Compleater Victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Enemies. The Hand of God has been ſo viſible in cutting off many of them; in driving others round the Nation; and in ſcattering ſome from one Kingdom to another, that ſome of themſelves have heavily curs'd their Pretended Heir to our three Kingdoms, as one Great Cauſe of all their Miſeries. The Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> indeed ſounds like an Immediate Heir to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> but that Adopted Child of Royal Grace might have been as properly call'd King of <hi>Salom</hi> as Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> for we know <hi>neither his Father, nor Mother, nor Deſcent; neither his Beginning of Days,</hi> nor (ſince he is got into <hi>France</hi>) are we like to hear of <hi>his End of Life.</hi> So that (to borrow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of a Learned Paraphraſt concerning <hi>Melthizedeck</hi>) he ſtands in Story as a kind of Immortal Prince, without any Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour. Tho' this Cheat was too groſs to paſs with the more Diſcerning People, yet certainly it might, in time, have made a good After-Game for a great part of the Nation; and the longer ſuch an Impoſture had kept Poſſeſſion in the Minds of Men, it wou'd have been remov'd with greater Difficulty. Timely, therefore, did the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (too Wiſe to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152410:7"/>Impos'd on by a Pack of Women, Knaves and Jeſuites; and too Brave and Daring to be frighten'd out of his Undoubted Right by any <hi>Hunſlow</hi> Campaigns) Reſolve upon and prepare for the Deliverance of three Kingdoms from Popery and Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and on this Noted Day he came: He came the Great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of our Faith, and all that is dear to us in Mortality. And ſince Almighty God has been ſo Prodigiouſly Merciful to theſe Nations as to raiſe up ſuch a Mighty Deliverer for us in the Day of our Diſtreſs, let us (when we are out of the Throng of Worldly Concerns) conſider with our ſelves how little Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we have to be Diſſatisfy'd under the Preſent Government; or rather how highly our Careful Monarch has oblig'd us all to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet and do our own buſineſs</hi> and ſo, make his Reign eaſy unto him and a Bleſſing unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The Sun has not twice gone his Annual Round ſince God and King <hi>William</hi> went forth with our Army to Battle and to Victory: And can we already forget what Miſeries we Suffer'd and what we Fear'd? Had not the All-Wiſe God put a timely ſtop to the Violent Proceedings of ſome Bigotted Papiſts (who ſtrongly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenc'd the whole Party) we might eaſily have foreſeen that our Nation (in a ſhort time) wou'd have groan'd under all thoſe Miſeries which our Brethren (of the Reform'd Churches abroad) have ſuffer'd under the Unmerciful Powers of <hi>France.</hi> We cannot ſurely but remember, when men imagin'd craftily againſt us; and Gravely laid their Heads together in a Mock-Parliament Houſe, to undo us with One Conſent; when they ſaid (and were as good as their word) <hi>Come and let us take to our ſelves the Houſes of God in Poſſeſſion:</hi> And is it a Grateful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for a Deliverance from ſuch Inveterate and Implacable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and the Reſtoration of our Pure Publick Worſhip, for any to continue ſtill ſo fooliſh as to imitate the peeviſh <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> who deſir'd a Deliverance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and when they were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd as earneſtly wiſh'd to return unto their old Slavery. <hi>O ye Sons of Men!</hi> How long will ye live Diſſatisfy'd, as if you pray'd for nothing more than to have our Holy Altars again abus'd by Superſtition and Idolatry? <hi>how long will ye love Vanity?</hi> As if you wou'd be glad once more to ſee this Houſe of God ſinely Dreſs'd with Babies and Pictures; the Entertainment and Diverſion of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152410:8"/>&amp; Fools. Men ſhou'd conſider that as Relapſes in the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Body are commonly more Fatal than the Firſt Diſeaſe, ſo, ſhou'd we again fall under Popery, our Laſt Eſtate would be worſe that the Firſt. And ſhall any endeavour to bring upon themſelves and others their Former Miſeries, with an Unſupportable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of New Calamities? Let us therefore be ſo Truly Wiſe as to <hi>Commune with our own Hearts</hi> about theſe things; and <hi>be ſtill</hi> under the Preſent Diſpenſation of Providence. Surely (whatſoever may be the Opinions of any Intereſted Perſons in our own Kingdoms) Forreign Nations will Condemn us for perfect Madmen, if we do not, in this our day, ſo conſider the Things that belong unto our Peace, as to ſit ſtill under our own Vines and Fig-Trees, and cheerfully eat the Fruit of our own, and of our Royal Maſter's Labours. Since we have the greateſt reaſon to addreſs unto our King as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did to his moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Faelix, Seeing that by thee we enjoy great Quietneſs, and very Worthy Deeds are done unto this Nation by thy Providence, we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it always, and in all places with all thankfulneſs;</hi> Seeing we are oblig'd unto ſo Juſt an Acknowledgment, ſurely we ſhou'd be ſo far from harbouring any Seditious Murmurings or Diſloyal Thoughts, that we ſhou'd rather every night (before we give any Sleep unto our Eyes or Slumber to our Eye-lids upon our Bed) earneſtly beg a Bleſſing upon that Royal Perſon thro' whoſe moſt Generous Affection, moſt Undaunted Courage and moſt Prudent Conduct we all (under God) do dwell in Safety all the Day, and lie down in Peace at Night. Shou'd any Diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd Perſons object againſt this, that ſince the Papiſts Live and are Mighty, 'tis in vain for any Preachers to talk of dwelling ſafely; I reply to ſuch in our Saviour's words, <hi>why are ye fearful, O ye of little Faith?</hi> Since God has at ſundry time, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers manners deliver'd their Fathers and themſelves from a great Death; from the <hi>Lyon</hi> and from the <hi>Bear,</hi> they ought with the United Strength of Faith and Reaſon, to conclude that (if they put their Truſt in him) he will yet deliver them from ev'ry Uncircumcis'd <hi>Philiſtine.</hi> And I wou'd have them conſider more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over (as a full Anſwer to all ſuch Unreaſonable Murmurings) that it is not their Buſineſs to underſtand the Deep Intrigues of State; and that it muſt be a very Impertinent Boldneſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152410:8"/>into the Secret Reaſons of them: let them therefore mind what more nearly concerns them, and (particularly) at this time, the Generous Spirit &amp; Quiet Carriage of <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> under the loſs of his own Eſtate; as it is written for our Inſtruction in the 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30. When the King had given part of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to the Treacherous <hi>Ziba,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou and</hi> Ziba <hi>divide the Land: Mephiboſheth</hi> (in the Tranſport of his Unmanageable Joy, at the General Happineſs of the Nation, upon King <hi>David</hi>'s returning home from Battle) does not only conſent to what King <hi>David</hi> granted unto <hi>Ziba</hi> (his Malicious Enemy) but (as if the Safety of a King, on the Preſervation of whoſe Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Publick Welfare did depend, had been a ſufficient Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any Loyal, Affectionate Subject) he thus reſigns his whole Eſtate; <hi>Yea, let him</hi> (let even <hi>Ziba</hi> that labour'd to take away my Life and Reputation) <hi>take all, ſeeing that my Lord the King is come again in Peace to his own Houſe.</hi> The Application of this Hiſtorical Paſſage being very eaſy, I hope you will make it unto your ſelves: for I cannot allow my ſelf the Liberty of any further Enlargement. To cloſe all therefore; Since we have now ſuch a Godly Proteſtant King and ſuch a Pious Proteſtant Queen upon the Throne, as our Kingdoms have never enjoy'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: Since God has Signally Bleſs'd with many Victories (ſhall I ſay, or with one continu'd Conqueſt) our Glorious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral (whoſe Immortal Actions, not only the Preſent Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but late Poſterity (after all that their Gratitude can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form) muſt leave to be Compleatly Rewarded in a rieher world, <hi>when God ſhall have put all Enemies under his Feet; even the Laſt Enemy that ſhall be deſtroy'd, Death it ſelf;</hi>) In a word, Since God has Mercifully Anſwer'd all our Prayers, and Diſappointed all our Unreaſonable Fears and Jealouſies; let not the harſh, Ungratefull Voice of Murmuring interrupt our more ſweet, acceptable Acclamatinons of Joy: <hi>but Stand in awe, and ſin not againſt God or his Anointed; Commune with your own Hearts upon your Beds and be Still.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
